Thomas H. Robbins Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Thomas H. Robbins Papers 1918-1971 (bulk 1920-1962)
MSS84346
Robbins, Thomas H. (Thomas Hinckley), 1900-1972
2,250 items
11 containers plus 1 classified
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States naval officer. Correspondence, duty orders, logbooks, biographical material, speeches, and other papers relating to Robbins's naval career and emphasizing his specialty in naval aviation.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Robbins, Thomas H. (Thomas Hinckley), 1900-1972.
Organizations
Sandpiper (Minesweeper); United States. Navy--Aviation.; United States. Navy.
Subjects
Aeronautics.; Aircraft industry--Military aspects.; Airplanes, Military.; Military intelligence.; Military weapons.; Naval aviation.; Naval history, Modern--20th century.; Navies.; Warships.
Places
Aleutian Islands (Alaska)--Surveys.; Europe--Politics and government.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Thomas H. Robbins, U.S. naval officer, were given to the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Thomas H. Robbins are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1900, May 11 Born, Paris, France
1919 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1919 1922 Served consecutively aboard the Kroonland (liner), Utah (battleship), and Sturtevant (destroyer)
1922 1924 Served aboard the Scorpion (patrol vessel converted yacht) in Turkish waters
1923 1924 Served aboard Submarine Chaser No. 96 in the Black Sea
1924 1925 Served consecutively aboard the destroyers MacLeish and MacFarland
1925 1927 Instructor, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1928 Served aboard the Utah (battleship) Ordered for flight training and designated naval aviator, Naval Air Station, Pensacola, Fla.
1928 1929 Scouting Squadron Five-S (aviation unit), Concord (light cruiser)
1929 1931 Executive officer, Scouting Squadron Six-S (aviation unit) aboard the Cincinnati (light cruiser)
1930 Married Barbara Little
1931 1932 Assistant operations officer, Naval Air Station, Anacostia, D.C.
1932 1933 Aide to the chief of Bureau of Aeronautics, Navy Department, Washington, D.C.
1933 1935 Commander, Sandpiper (minesweeper)
1935 1936 Scouting Squadron Four-B, Langley (aircraft carrier)
1936 1937 Attended Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1937 1939 Aviation officer, Naval War College and Naval Torpedo Station, Newport, R.I.
1939 1940 Navigator, Lexington (aircraft carrier)
1940 1941 Aviation officer, staff of Commander Scouting Force and Commander Task Force Three
1941 Liaison officer between the Office of the Chief of Naval Operations and the commanding general, Army Air Force Command, Washington, D.C.
1942 Liaison officer between Headquarters, Commander in Chief, United States Fleet, and Army Air Force Combat Command, Washington, D.C.
1942 1943 Aviation plans officer, Headquarters, Commander in Chief, United States Fleet
1943 1944 Naval aviation officer, Army and Navy College, Washington, D.C.
1944 Received letter of commendation with authorization to wear the commendation ribbon Temporary duty, Air Force Pacific Fleet aboard the Essex (aircraft carrier)
1945 Commanding officer, Lexington (aircraft carrier) Received Legion of Merit with Combat Distinguishing Device "V"
1945 1948 Assigned consecutively to Office of the Deputy Chief of Naval Operations for Air, Office of the Chief of Naval Operations, and Office of the Secretary of the Navy
1948 1949 Commander, Carrier Division Seventeen
1949 1952 Navy member, Joint Strategic Survey Committee, Joint Chiefs of Staff, Washington, D.C.
1952 1953 Commander, Carrier Division Two
1953 1956 Chief of staff and later president, United States Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1957 1960 President, Navy Discharge Review Board, Bureau of Naval Personnel, Navy Department, Washington, D.C.
1960 1962 Commandant, Potomac River Naval Command, Naval Weapons Plant, Washington, D.C.
1962 Awarded a gold star in lieu of a second Legion of Merit Retired from the navy
1972, Dec. 12 Died, New London, Conn. [?]
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Thomas Hinckley Robbins (1900-1972) span the years 1918-1971, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1920-1962. The collection reflects a career devoted to naval aviation from the 1920s to the 1960s. Featured in the papers are official and personal correspondence, orders for duty, naval aviation log books, biographical information, speeches, and material relating to Robbins's service aboard the minesweeper Sandpiper.
Robbins's official correspondence contains routine information on examinations, appointments, naval personnel, and naval aviation. Of note in the correspondence are memoranda to naval intelligence on the inspections of airplanes by foreign dignitaries, foreign aviation activities, espionage, foreign ships and armaments, and meetings with individuals such as Rachid Montan Pacha, a Syrian leader visiting New York in 1925 to sell jewels. A majority of the personal correspondence is written to and from naval personnel relating to naval aviation, aircraft, aircraft companies, and European politics.
Material relating to the Sandpiper covers the period 1933-1935 when the ship sailed in Alaskan waters and participated in the Aleutian Islands survey expedition of 1935. Robbins's personal operations diary and narratives for this time are supplemented by newspaper articles written about the Sandpiper.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or subject and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Awards and certificates, 1949-1954, 1962, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
- Biographical information, 1930, 1943, 1953-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Cartoons by John Thomason, 1938, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Official (Box 1)
    - 1918-1954, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1955-1965, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Personal (Box 2)
    - 1927-1939, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1940-1946, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1947-1952 See also Classified, (6 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1953-1955, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1956-1957, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1958, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 6, Box 7)
    - 1959, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1960, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 7, Box 8)
    - 1961-1964, (5 folders) (Box 8)
- Lexington (aircraft carrier), 1939-1940, undated (Box 8)
- Log books for aviation, 1928-1959 (Box 9)
- Miscellany, 1946, undated (Box 9)
- Naval newspapers, 1921-1923 (Box 9)
- Orders for duty (Box 9)
  - 1919-1953, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1954-1964 (Box 10)
- Sandpiper (minesweeper) (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re Aleutian Islands survey expedition, 1935 (Box 10)
  - Narrative of activities, 1933-1935 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
  - Personal operations diary, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
- Speeches (Box 10)
  - 1946-1955, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1956-1962 (Box 11)
- Writings, 1939, 1956 (Box 11)
- Classified material (Box CL 1)
  - Correspondence (Box CL 1)
    - Personal (Box CL 1)
      - 1952 (Box CL 1)
        - 20 Oct. (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
        - 4 Dec. (Container 4) (Box CL 1)